we have our last presenter
who I believe was able to join us.
Yes.
Anna Marques da Silva.
Whenever you are ready, take it away.
Oh, I believe you might be needed.
And here you can hear you,
Anna.
You're muted.
Sorry.
Oh no trouble. No trouble at all.
Good afternoon everyone.
My presentation focuses on
how the notion of authorship
and generative literature evolved in time.
I see waves regarding the authorship
theory and generative poetics.
As an introduction, I will briefly address
the first definitions of
of generative literature,
as well as the importance of the notions
of a literary,
of the notion of a literary algorithm
in the dawn of the computer age.
Generative art was understood
within the framework
of conceptual esthetics as solo,
which stated
the idea becomes a machine
that makes the art.
What is at stake
here is the encoding into an algorithm
of an idea of what literature, the visual
arts, music, or any other language
may be, as well as the automation
of the processes that exhaust all possible
variations of the material expression
of such an idea.
Throughout the following decades,
different authors proposed different
theoretical perspectives
on what generative literature is,
but the affiliation
with conceptual esthetics remained.
Philip Boots,
co-founder of the group Slayer
in 1977 and 2012, observable
in 20 and 2003,
considered the code to be an integral part
of the literary work.
In the near technical process.
For boots, what is understood to be
a generative work is the entire system
which is constituted by the code,
the database, the processing device,
the author, each
specific textual configuration generated
at each iteration, and the virtual
whole that comprises all possible
textual configurations
contained within the programed model.
And we might add.
Of course, the reader Jean-Pierre
Balak, French pioneer of computer
generated
narrative, defined generative literature
as the production of literary texts
in continuous mutation
through a specific dictionary
and the set of rules for him.
A textual generator is an automaton,
and I'm quoting an automaton capable
of producing a psychologically
and limited quantity of acceptable objects
within a previously defined
domain of communication bulb.
This proposed a definition
intimately linked to establish discursive
conventions. For now, awards are proven.
A textual generator is a tool,
and I'm quoting for textual performance,
which may be used to play
a variety of compositions,
and for the Portuguese poet Pedro Barbosa,
a generative text and I quote.
Aims aims to develop through the machine
a literary textual algorithm
until its capacity for
meaning is exhausted
within a given field of possibilities.
Taken together, the proposals
by bulb, boots, Prune and Barbosa
merged the notion of generative texts
with the notion of textual generator
defining the text from its model
and its mechanism.
If, however, we aim
for a definition of generative literature
that goes beyond the mere mechanism,
the idea of a literary algorithm
to which the hinted becomes crucial,
such an idea is virtually implicit
in any generative literary text,
but seems to have never been explicitly
put forward following the path
indicated by the aforementioned authors.
But fine tuning it a little bit,
we can define a generative literary text
as a text program to be generated
through computational processes
that creatively explored
the exhaustion of variations
around the self-reflexive
model of literature.
The particularity of
generative textual lies in its dual
machining dimension.
The text is a concrete,
not metaphorical, machine, understood
as a complex, manipulable device
for producing new texts.
A generator is the set of processes
determined by
and contained in a program
conceived by the author.
From these there arise
to to distinct and interrelated
interrelated levels of writing,
the authorial writing of the instructions
and the machine
execution of the instructions.
The question of writing
and authorship is one of the questions
that deserve more attention
in generative poetics.
Indeed, no other literary form
has interfered more dramatically
with authorship.
The first theoretical approaches to this
problem
were proposed
in the last quarter of the 20th century.
The Portuguese for the Portuguese
pioneer were Bosa.
Authorship and I quote
can only encompass the project, the model,
and the structure of the set of texts
to be realized that meaning and formed
and form assumed
by each of its multiple variations,
escape its author
to a greater or lesser degree, and
quote.
And this was written in 1977.
Later, Jean-Pierre
proposed the notion of meta author.
The author,
he says, is one who accepts responsibility
for the text produced
but does not feel fully involved in them.
Establishes the distance
between writing and subjectivity.
What the what the writes is
in fact a machine,
but wrote this in 1997.
In the decades
following, the first experiments
with automatic text generation,
several authors
published works
focused on remix, pastiche, and parody.
Generative literature
became increasingly dialogic,
and the conception of distributed
authorship emerged more than a meta
authorship centered on the conception
and control of the code.
Distributed authorship is shared
among communities of authors
and readers who adapt and remix code
circulating on the network.
The concept also refers more generally,
the concept of generative
of distributed authorship
also refers more generally more generally,
to the cognitive assemblages that
articulate the human and the machining.
Examples of distributed authorship
include Montfort's generators,
notably
the already quoted, cited, referred sorry
Scott was adapted by
a number of new authors to generate
vastly different types of texts.
Another example is John Cayley's work,
namely crucial pieces
such as how it is and Common Tanks
or the Listeners works that expose
and support the logic of globalized
techno capitalist capitalism,
operating as a pharmacological critique.
To use Stigler, terms of the capture
of human language and function,
and functioning as allegorical devices
to refer to Alexander Galloway
that revealed digital culture
as a culture of cybernetic control.
The works of this second wave underscore
the collaborative nature of the network
as a literary space, bringing to the floor
the notion of writing as a proliferation
of writings and allusions,
and the notion of reading
as a proliferation of readings,
while at the same time
enabling a deeper understanding
of technical mediation and end up
the landscape of digital culture.
In more recent experiments,
strategies of authorial inscription
and in distant reading,
sorry distance writing
and the work of the human in the loop,
either before
or after the moment of machine generation,
and reinforce the notion
of writing as a series
of different layers of composition
strategies.
Economical example is the work
of Canadian poet Jarvi, particularly
his long term project Big Data Poetry,
and one of its iterations rewrites.
In this hybrid writing experiments,
the first layers
of composition correspond
to the training of a neural network
and to the fine tuning of its parameters,
all done by Java.
The second layer of work is the machine
generation
itself, and I would have not exactly
of texts and not exactly of language,
but that discussion would fit another
talk.
Finally, the third layer of work
corresponds to the authorial
editing of the generated output.
Only after this series of different
writing moments
can we consider the bones of rewrites
to be proper bones, instead of machine
labor or mimesis of a given database
when possible.
Conclusion.
To be drawn from this brief
sketch of the evolution of the notion
of authorship in generative literature
is that, contrary to the most
to the most obvious
predictions, theater is very much alive.
In fact, the automation of writing
reinforces the author's role
in the conceptualization
of of what the literary work may be.
Hence, the centrality of the concept
of a literary algorithm
and of self-reflexive
notion of the literary
as writing tools
become more and more opaque.
Literary cyber writing increasingly claims
more autonomy,
finding ways to inscribe authorial voice
and intent.
Generative literary texts are no longer
small,
self-contained, autonomous machines
controlled by a meta author.
With the rise of the web,
they became embedded in larger systems,
where the circulation of texts
and the networked dynamics
of writing and reading gave way
to the distribution of authorship.
Now, in the age of AI,
literary authors of generative textually
no longer explore
just the programing of text generators,
but also the training,
prompting, and editing.
Generative literature
is increasingly permeated
by systems whose logistics conflict
with the domain of the literary.
In fact, in such an environment saturated
not only with technical
but also with political layers
or surreal agency necessarily conflicts
with an increasing number
of other agencies, some of them explicit.
Many others, given.
Authors of generative literature,
does explore
not only the computation of language
and its embedding in a networked
discursive field, but also an increasingly
complex mesh of technical,
political, conflicting voices
because of this friction.
Authors of generative literature
and I mean literature, not me message
and not morphologies during
those times are in the singular position
of demonstrating through practice
what is and what is not Sable.
Carving out spaces of literary possibility
within the cybernetic landscape.
Thank you very much.